<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-valin-netvc-l1tw-00"
     ipr="noDerivativesTrust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Screencasting and L1TW">Screencasting Considerations and L1-Tree Wavelet Coding</title>

 <author initials="JM." surname="Valin" fullname="Jean-Marc Valin">
   <organization>Mozilla</organization>
   <address>
     <postal>
       <street>331 E. Evelyn Avenue</street>
       <city>Mountain View</city>
       <region>CA</region>
       <code>94041</code>
       <country>USA</country>
     </postal>
     <email>jmvalin@jmvalin.ca</email>
   </address>
 </author>


    <date day="6" month="July" year="2015" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes a screencasting encoding mode based on the Haar wavelet
      transform and L1-tree wavelet (L1TW) coding.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Screensharing is an important application for an Internet video codec.
      Screensharing content differs from photographic images in many ways, including:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Text: screenshots often contain anti-aliased text on a perfectly flat background.
        This makes ringing artefacts highly perceptible. Also, typical photographic codecs
        based on the discrete cosine transform (DCT) cannot take advantage of the
        fact that the background often has a constant colour.</t>
        <t>Lines and edges. Screenshots often contain perfectly straight horizontal and/or
        vertical lines. They appear in window frames, toolbars, widgets, spreadsheets, etc.
        DCT-based codecs can represent those lines and edges, but not as compactly as
        codecs like PNG.</t>
        <t>Reduced number of colours: Screenshots are much less "noisy" than photographic
        images. It is common for a certain region of an image to only contain a handful of
        different colours, another property we would like to exploit in a video codec.</t>
        <t>A very common motion pattern in screensharing content is the displacement of
        windows. This typically involves rectangular boundaries.</t>
      </list>
      The technique described in this document only deals with still images for now and
      focuses on the problem of efficiently coding anti-aliased text. While it is implemented
      for the Daala <xref target="Daala-website"/> codec.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Haar Wavelet">
      <t>The Haar wavelet <eref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haar_wavelet"/>
      is the simplest of all orthogonal wavelets, and also the only one with linear
      phase. We use the Haar transform both because it is spatially compact and because
      it makes it easy to switch between a wavelet transform and the DCT. 
      </t>

      <t>In 1-D, a single level of the Haar transform is expressed as:
<figure align="center">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
            ___
[ y0 ]     / 1  [  1 1 ] [ x0 ]
[    ] =  / --- [      ] [    ]
[ y1 ]   v   2  [ -1 1 ] [ x1 ]
]]></artwork>
</figure>
      </t>

      <t>The 2-D Haar transform is implemented from a 2x2 lifting Haar kernel:
<figure align="center">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
inputs: x0, x1, x2, x3
x0 <= x0 + x2
x3 <= x3 - x1
tmp <= (x0 - x3) >> 1
x1 <= tmp - x1
x2 <= tmp - x2
x0 <= x0 - x1
x3 <= x3 + x2
outputs: x0, x1, x2, x3
]]></artwork>
</figure>
      This kernel has perfect reconstruction, making it also useful for lossless compression. 
      </t>

      <t>The kernel above is applied on 5 levels for 32x32 superblocks. The
      resulting wavelet coefficients are quantized non-uniformly using the
      following quantization scales relative to the DC quantizer (from low
      frequency to high frequency):
<figure align="center">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
horizontal/vertical: [1.0, 1.0, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0]
diagonal:            [1.0, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0, 3.0]
]]></artwork>
</figure>

      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="L1-Tree Coding">
      <t>Like other wavelet coding methods such as EZW and SPIHT, we code the wavelet
      coefficients using trees. The main difference however is that rather than being
      based on the maximum coefficient value in a tree, this technique is based on
      the sum of the absolute values of all coefficients in the tree. Let x(i,j)
      denote the quantized wavelet coefficient at position (i,j), the children of x(i,j)
      are x(2*i,2*j), x(2*i,2*j+1), x(2*i+1,2*j), and x(2*i+1,2*j+1). The absolute sum
      of the tree rooted in (i,j) is defined recursively as:
<figure align="center">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
S(i,j) = |x(i,j)| + S(2*i,2*j) + S(2*i,2*j+1)
       + S(2*i+1,2*j) + S(2*i+1,2*j+1),
]]></artwork>
</figure>
      with S(i,j)=0 for i or j >= N. C(i,j) is defined as S(i,j) - |x(i,j)|.
      </t>

      <t>Coefficient coding starts at the root of each of the three "direction trees":
      (1,0), (0,1), and (1,1). At each level we code the value of |x(i,j)| using a
      cumulative density function adapted based on the value of S(i,j). Coding |x(i,j)|
      implies that the value of C(i,j) is known to the decoder, so it does not need
      to be coded. Three symbols are then required to encode each of the new roots:
      S(2*i,2*j), S(2*i,2*j+1), S(2*i+1,2*j), and S(2*i+1,2*j+1). </t>

      <t>At the top level, we have S(0,0) = S(1,0) + S(0,1) + S(1,1), so that completely
      flat blocks can be coded with a single S(0,0)=0 symbol. The DC is coded separately.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Results">
      <t>The coded images obtained with the Haar transform and L1TW have far better
      subjective visual quality than those obtained with the lapped DCT or with JPEG, and of
      comparable quality to those obtained with x264
      <eref target="http://www.videolan.org/developers/x264.html"/> and x265
      <eref target="http://x265.org/"/>. An example image at
      around 0.35 bit/pixel is provided at
      <eref target="http://jmvalin.ca/video/haar_example/"/>.</t>

      <t>While the technique
      presented here works relatively well on the example above, there are still
      cases where it performs significantly worse than x265. These include gradients,
      such as those in toolbars and window titlebars, and long horizontal and vertical
      lines such as those found in spreadsheets. These cases should improve once we
      implement the ability to dynamically switch between the lapped DCT and the Haar
      transform. Other ways of improving performance on long lines and edges would be
      to extend to use a different 2D wavelet decomposition, or use an overcomplete
      basis.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Objective Evaluation">
      <t>As a first step for evaluating screensharing quality, we have added a small
        collection of screenshot images to the "Are We Compressed Yet?"
        <eref target="https://arewecompressedyet.com/"/> website, under the
        "screenshots" set name. 
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Development Repository">
      <t>The algorithms in this proposal are being developed as part of
      Xiph.Org's Daala project. The code is available in the Daala git
      repository at <eref target="https://git.xiph.org/daala.git"/>.
      See <xref target="Daala-website"/> for more information.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This draft has no security considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Timothy B. Terriberry for useful feedback and for designing
      the 2-D Haar lifting kernel.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Informative References">

    <reference anchor="Daala-website" target="https://xiph.org/daala/">
      <front>
        <title>Daala website</title>
        <author><organization/></author>
        <date/>
      </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Xiph.Org Foundation" value=""/>
    </reference>

    </references>
</back>
</rfc>
